# MEHMET FURKAN ŞAHİN

Cell Phone: +90 539 2026442 E-mail: sahinffurkan@gmail.com GitHub: /furkansahin Personal web-site: mfsh.in

A passionate senior year Computer Engineering student with strong knowledge in algorithms and valuable work experience in C, Java, Python, PostgreSQL, and data visualization.

## **EDUCATION**

2012-2017 June Bilkent University, Computer Science, Ankara, TURKEY: B.Sc. granted comprehensive scholarship.

CGPA: 3.69/4.00

Ranked 659th. in Nationwide University Entrance Exam among 1.8 million students.

2015-Fall École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland: Exchange program, Computer Science (IN, B.Sc.)

## **EXPERIENCE**

**2016 October, Publication, The cBioPortal for cancer genomics and its application in precision oncology:** Author, detailed information can be found in the link.

**2016 July - 2016 August, Institute of High Performance Computing, A\*Star, Singapore:** Research Assistant. Worked on a 3D robotic arm model which can play ping pong.

**2016 May - 2016 July, Citus Data, Istanbul:** Software Engineering Internship, created percentile approximations extension for PostgreSQL. Percentile queries are speeded up 400x.

**2015 August - 2016 January, Human-Computer Interaction Group - EPFL, Switzerland:** Undergrad Researcher, developed a data visualization tool for MOOCs data with D3 JavaScript library.

# SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS

2012-Present, Bilkent University High Honor Student

2015, TUBITAK (Turkish Science Foundation) Undergraduate Researcher Scholarship

**2016-2013**, **IEEEXtreme 10.0 - 8.0-7.0 Programming Competition:** As a team of three undergraduate students, which is named TechWeb, ranked 1st. in Turkey, 30th. In IEEE Region 8, 73rd. in the world among 2500 teams competing throughout the world.

#### **PROJECTS**

**CrypDist, Senior Project - Present:** CrypDist is a blockchain based encrypted content distribution network. The project aims to avoid data access blocks and reduce the time needed to deliver big data. I take responsibilities on the development of distribution system.

**Section Checker Bot, Bilkent University 2016 - 2017:** A Telegram Bot available via @sectionchecker\_bot in Telegram Messaging App. It is checks available quotas for the desired courses of Bilkent students. The bot gave service for more than 500 people during the 2017 Spring registration term.

**HDR**, Citus Data - 2016: HDR is a Histogram based percentile approximation extension for PostgreSQL database systems. It provides 400x speed increase with 0.0001 error ratio. The whole project is handled by myself.

**Github Community Detection, Bilkent University - 2016:** The tool is created as a course project for CS 425 - Algorithms for Web-Scale Data with one more colleague. GitHub user data is collected in a breadth first manner for a specific user and by applying Walktrap algorithm. We visualized 10 k people in clusters according to their common features.

**Beatify, EPFL - 2015:** Beatify is created as a group project with 2 more colleagues. It is a music player android app which finds the best music from your Spotify account according to the instant heart rate of the user. I implemented Spotify integration.

**cBioPortal - Network transformation, MSKCC - 2015:** Network tab of cBioPortal is transformed from a flash based version to Cytoscape JS. The whole project is handled by myself.

# **COMPUTER SKILLS**

Programming: Java, C/C++, SQL(PostgreSQL, MySQL), Python, Android, D3 JS, Cytoscape JS.

Operating Systems: OS X, Microsoft Windows, Linux

Interests: Distributed Systems, Databases, Algorithms, Big Data, Cloud Architecture, Mobile applications.

Courses: CS 425 - Algorithms for Web-Scale Data, CS 476 - Automata Theory and Formal Languages, CS 342 - Operating Systems, CS 353 Database Systems, CS 315 - Programming Languages, EPFL - Functional Programming, EPFL - Lab on Apps Development for Tablets and Smartphones, EPFL - Projet en Informatique I.

## **MEMBERSHIP & PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

2014 – 2015 Young Guru Academy Conference Participant

**2013 – 2015 Bilkent IEEE Coordinator – International IEEE Member:** Coordinated volunteer students to organise technical and social events and trainings about courses to help other Bilkent students.